Valentin EKEU TIEMENI

Green Card holder - No Sponsorship required

Hard worker; Natural problem solver; Analytical thinker with strong interpersonal skills; Calm under pressure.

Landover, Maryland 20785

+1 (240) 441-7066

ektiva2013@gmail.com

Website: https://ektiva.github.io/

Summary

I am a Software Engineer with experience building multi-tiered applications, created full-stack .NET Application with C#, Angular, MVC, SQL, JavaScript, HTML, and CSS. In addition, I have an in-depth understanding of Object-Oriented Programming, Agile development methodology, analysis, designs and SOLID principle. I'm a really motivated person and able to learn new technologies or concepts very fast. I'm capable of handling multiple tasks and I have strong customer service skills.

Professional Experience

Software Engineer | Regency Management Services, LLC - Brandywine, MD

Feb. 2020 - Oct. 2020

Working in Agile environment with a team to migrate a web application build with classic ASP (vbscript) to ASP.NET Core web application. Responsibilities:

- Research, evaluate, recommend, and implement technical solutions.
- Use Characterization test to understand the behavior of the classic ASP web application and create documentation for the new project.
- Designed and implemented Auth Gateway for authentication by scaffolding ASP.Net identity.
- Elaborate the Coding Standards and Best Programming Practices for the team.
- Designed and implemented the different model including the hierarchyld type and fluent validation.
- Create the initial database instance using EF code first and write consistent LINQ query to access SQL Server database.
- Implement RESTful ASP.NET Web APIs using HttpClient and Ajax to communicate with database.
- Managed database structure using Fluid API and data formatting with Data Annotations including Regex.
- Completed unit and integration testing with MSTest and xUnit unit tests in C#, with Swagger for API and with Jasmine-based tests run with Karma in
- Configure and use azure pipeline for CI/CD, Setup and managed azure app insight to monitor the lives applications.
- Build a reactive and responsive UI for the client side login, registration and merchandize with Angular 8.
- Setup and implemented azure service bus (topic) for asynchronous transfer of data and state between our different services.
- Design and implemented the repository pattern.
- Setup and implemented Redis database for in-memory cache.

Software Engineer | Revature - Reston, MD

June 2019 – January 2020

Full Stack development including design, coding, unit testing, integration testing, debugging, configuring, and documenting of software solutions using .Net(C#), Angular, ASP .NET MVC, SQL, Azure Devops, JavaScript, HTML, CSS...

Responsibilities:

- Involved and participated in the overall application lifecycle of multiple projects.
- Designed and implemented MVC design pattern.
- Setup and implemented Redis database for in-memory cache.
- Writing, implementing and testing code, refining and rewriting it as necessary.
- Tested functionality with unit tests written using Visual Studio NUnit Test .Net core.
- Resolve complex technical design issues (Date problem, EF migration, many to many relationship, communications between model-view-
- Designed and Build reactive Angular front-ends using custom services to asynchronously deliver RxJS Observables with data from HttpClient calls to API.
- Develop and consume (from Angular) REST (WebAPI) and SOAP (WCF) based services.
- Tested API with Postman and Swagger and ensure that data is presented in JSON format, visit Can I Use to optimize HTTML code and user browser experience.
- Collaborate with colleagues (using Git/Github and slack) to ensure successful implementation of changes to existing system.
- Set Up local container registry for test deployments/builds.
- Override the OnModelCreating method and use the ModelBuilder API to configure the model.

Production Supervisor | Walmart – Washington Blvd, Arbutus, MD

October 2017 - June 2019

Manage production team and Develop best practices, routines and innovative solutions to improve production rates and quality of output.

Metrology/Application Engineer | PISE - Cameroon

March 2014 - Sept. 2017

- Responsible of metrology and innovation department and supervision of a high performing team that is capable of analysing, troubleshooting, and repairing broken equipment, as well as performing preventive maintenance tasks.
- Designed and Implemented an Information System to manage Metrology department (Java + SQL).
- Write complex gueries, Stored Procedures and apply RDBMS concepts to the Information System
- Write JSP and Servlets to add functionality to web application based on requirements
- Develop UIs with JSP, JavaScript, HTML and CSS
- Use J2EE design patterns to create application, including utilizing EJB for business logic
- Use core Java Technologies like Multithreading, Collections and Exception handling mechanisms
- Develop various JavaBeans components for implementing business logic.
- Designed and developed API with all the CRUD capabilities using SOAP

Application Engineer | AMLA - Yaounde, Cameroon

Jan 2013 - February 2014

- Analysis, Design and Implementation of a Gauging and Tank-Strapping Software (using Java Swing & SQL) based on a volumetric approach and the information System of the Station, using scientific analysis and mathematical models.

Responsibilities:

- Designed the entire application using UML and OOP design pattern and the database using SQL design pattern.
- Get user requirement from the company COO and translate into technical requirements.
- Modeling the application (use case diagram, class diagram, sequence diagram, deployment diagram, prototype, calculation model...)
- Define and implement the business logic (volumetric vs geometry tank-strapping)
- Build responsive, functional and great looking UI of the application using Java Swing, NetBeans and 3rd party library look and feel.
- Use PowerAMC to design class diagram and generate custom code source for java and PHP and Script for SQL.

Education

Bootcamp / Software Engineering | Revature - Reston, Virginia

July 2019 - September 2019

- Project base Bootcamp where we created full stack web application using .Net and Angular curriculum, including C#, SQL, ASP.NET MVC, JavaScript, JQuery, Ajax, HTML, CSS, Angular 6, Azure DevOps, Docker, Algorithm and Data Structure....

Master Degree / Design Engineering | National Advanced School of Engineering, Yaounde

Sept. 2010 - July 2013

- Engineering and Production Management; Design and Development of New Products and Production Systems; Quality; Information System (Databases, Networking, Programming); Operational Research, Human Resources Management and Ergonomics, Health, Safety and Environment

Bachelor's Degree in Mathematics (2008) | University of Yaounde 1

Sept. 2004 - July 2008

Numerical Analysis, Game Theory, Descriptive Statistics and Probability; Operational Research, Scientific Computing and Data Analysis, Decisional Statistic, Optimisation.

Skills and Abilities

Technical Skills

- Web Technologies: ASP.NET Web API, .NET MVC, Web Services, HTML5, AJAX & JQuery, CSS, Angular.
- Programming Language: JavaScript, Java, C#, Python, VB/VBA, C+, Matlab, PHP.
- Database & Storage: SQLite, SQL, SQL Server, MySQL, NoSQL, Redis, ACCESS, AWS, Microsoft Azure SQL Database.
- Devops: Kubernetes, Postman, Docker, Git, SonarCloud, Azure DevOps (CI/CD, Application Insights, Service Bus, Resource group, SQL server/database, App Service...).
- Amazon Web Services: IAM, AWS EC2, AWS EBS, AWS AMI.
- Strong proficiency with Microsoft Office applications and statistical tools (Excel, Word, Minitab, PowerPoint...)
- Lean Six Sigma green belt level capability with strong Knowledge in application of DMAIC, DFSS and Lean Tools.
- Solid understanding of Object Oriented Programming, SOLID principle, business and IT processes.

Communication & interpersonal Skills

- Excellent team-working and Leadership abilities. Good integration in the workplace.
- Eager, ambitious, and adaptable to change
- Excellent attention to detail and strong organizational and time management abilities
- Heightened sense of Work Ethics and Discipline Standards, practical abilities, rigor and effectiveness skills.

Language

- French: Native
- English: Professional Proficiency